Register of the American Relief Administration Russian operational records
Hoover Institution Archives
- London Office, Russia File, 1919-1923
  - Corn, August. Correspondence about the distribution of corn for the purpose of feeding the railway personnel and the agreement on turning over the grain to the Soviet Railway authorities for distribution to the workmen to ensure the movement of food supplies to famine areas in an efficient manner, 1922 March- (Folder 7)
  - Crimea, Reports and correspondence regarding the Crimean government's proposal to use gold and gold coins as a form of payment for grain purchases from the United States. Includes material relating to the negotiations between the ARA and the Crimean authorities about using a third party for the changing hand of gold and grain shipments without directly involving the ARA, 1921-1922. (Folder 8-9)
  - Crops, Includes tables, some statistics on sowing, estimated figures on relief needs and plans for meeting them, memoranda on the Russian crop situation based on all types of grains and cereals, and correspondence regarding the aid of foreign organizations in combatting, 1921 August-1923 June. (Folder 10)
  - Donations, Letters and telegrams regarding amount of funds donated to the relief operations from individuals, private organizations, and societies, 1921-1923. (Box 499, Folder 1-2)
    Available on microfilm reels 582 and 583
  - Economic and political conditions, 1921 August-1923 June. Includes typescripts of articles published in the Economist about the new economic policy in Russia, news summaries on relief work in Russia, translations of speeches by the Soviet Commissar of Foreign Affairs, a draft of the state budget for balance sheets of the banks and credit societies; a document entitled "The Legal Conditions for the Operation of Foreign Capital in Russia," and correspondence reporting political activities such as the execution of members of the old Famine Relief Committee and the anti-Soviet uprising in Petrograd, 1922/1923 (Folder 3)
    Available on microfilm reel 583
  - Equipment, 1921 Septemeber- Correspondence and telegrams requesting equipment such as typewriters, motorcycles, adding machines, mimeograph machines, and other miscellaneous machinery and supplies, 1922 February. (Folder 4)
  - European Relief Council, Correspondence mainly between the London Office, New York Office, and the Russian Unit discussing issues relating to relief activities of religious organization in Russia such as the Quakers, Mennonites, and Lutherans. Includes letters of introduction of Quakers personnel, inquiries about passport policy for non ARA relief workers, and reports on illegal religious activities by various religious groups, 1921 August-1922 April.
    - 1921-1922 (Folder 5-6)
      Available on microfilm reel 583 and 584
    - 1922-1923 (Box 500, Folder 1-3)
      Available on microfilm reels 584 and 585
  - Finances, Correspondence regarding accounts paid out and general financial matters of the relief operations such as currency exchanges, receipts, and payments to the London Office. Includes reports from the ARA to the President of the U.S. on the Congressional appropriation, instructions on handling subsistence accounts and credits opened to affiliated organizations, outlines of a bookkeeping system for salary and subsistence accounts, letters of request for financial and reimbursement statements, and inquiries of cash transactions, 1921 October-1923 April. (Folder 4-5)
    Available on microfilm reel 586
  - Food (Box 501)
    - Draft service, Established to provide American food to individuals and groups in Russia. Includes the Food Draft Agreement with the Russian Socialist Federative Soviet Republic that food drafts be sold outside of Russia and the beneficiaries in Russia receive food packages at designated ARA warehouses upon presentation of sufficient documents, memoranda on procedures to handle food remittances for the New York Office and European offices, price sheets for average cost on different commodities, samples of application form, reports on distribution of sales according to delivery points in Russia, summaries of application sales, bulk sales, and Eurelcon sales, and statistics showing distribution according to delivery districts in Russia, 1921-1923.
      - General
        - 1921-1922 (Folder 1)
          Available on microfilm reel 587
        - 1922-1923 (Folder 2)
      - Bulk sales. Correspondence concerning procedural matters in handling large quantity of food remittance sales to organizations and committees
        - 1921-1922 (Folder 3)
          Available on microfilm reel 588
        - 1922-1923 (Box 502, Folder 1)
      - Intelligentsia, Correspondence about providing food relief for a group of intellectual Russian refugees in Berlin, 1921-1923. (Folder 2)
        Available on microfilm reel 589
      - Local sales, Mostly correspondence and telegrams reporting remittance sales to local areas, 1921-1923. (Folder 3)
      - Supplies, Correspondence regarding the quantity of foodstuffs to stock in warehouses, 1921-1923. (Folder 4)
    - Movements and routes, Mostly telegrams regarding shipments of foods, sailing itineraries, and ports availability for unloading goods, 1921-1922.
      - 1921 August-1922 April (Folder 5-6)
        Available on microfilm reel 590
      - May, 1922 April- (Box 503, Folder 1)
        Available on microfilm reel 591
    - Packages, Correspondence noting local advertisements and publicity for the food remittance program and concerns of closure for the Russian food and clothing remittance program. Includes one map of Russia outlining the parts of Russia where ARA can deliver food packages, lists of outstanding remittances, list of food contents and substitute items when regular commodity not available, publicity materials, addresses of the ARA food remittance stations, statements on the condition of food remittance deliveries, and sketches of food remittance districts, 1921-1923.
      - 1921 August-1922 January (Folder 2)
      - 1922
        - January-July (Folder 3-4)
          Available on microfilm reel 592
        - July-August (Box 504, Folder 1-2)
          Available on microfilm reel 593
    - Quality of foodstuffs, Correspondence regarding food damaged during shipping either by sea water, heating, or sweat, and the necessary reconditioning of the food packages before shipping to final destination, 1922. (Folder 3)
    - Remittances, Correspondence by both beneficiaries and donors inquiring about delivery status of food remittances and reports of lost food packages and parcels. Include lists and reports of pending delivery food remittances, statistical figures for monthly food draft sales, and letters of appreciation from recipients, 1921-1923.
      - 1921 December-1922 March (Folder 4-5)
        Available on microfilm reel 594
      - 1922 (Box 505)
        - March-May (Folder 1-2)
          Available on microfilm reel 595
        - May-August (Folder 3-4)
          Available on microfilm reel 596
      - 1922 September-1923 April (Box 506, Folder 1-2)
        Available on microfilm reel 597
      - September, 1923 April- (Folder 3-4)
        Available on microfilm reel 598
    - Sales, Correspondence inquiring about the status of the food draft sales to various organizations. Include price lists for food and commodities, letters of request for refunds, inquiries about delivery status, reports of sale transactions and other accounting matters, 1921-1923.
      - 1921 September-1922 June (Folder 5)
    - 1922 June-1923 September (Box 507, Folder 1-2)
      Available on microfilm reel 599
  - Forage, Correspondence about the need to purchase a certain amount of oats to be used as forage in the famine districts, 1921-1923. (Folder 3)
  - Insurance of personnel, Correspondence inquiring about insurance coverage for ARA personnel working in Russia, 1921-1923. (Folder 4)
    Available on microfilm reel 600
  - Medical file
    - General correspondence, Correspondence requesting more purchases of medical supplies such as vaccines and first aid medicine and requesting that medical personnel handle and inspect medical supplies. Includes draft agreement between the ARA and the Russian Zemstvos and Towns committees regarding the organization of the supply of medicine chests for household use to Russia, medical personnel; an executive order relating to the transfer of medical supplies from government departments to the ARA; memoranda on accounting procedures for medical supplies, and a map outlining the number of epidemic diseases in Russia by cities, 1921-1923.
      - 1921 August-1922 April (Folder 5-6)
      - 1922 May-1923 June (Box 508, Folder 1-2)
        Available on microfilm reel 601
    - Reports, Reports submitted by the medical units summarizing the various activities of the medical division. Includes photographs of the medical department, a map showing monthly medical relief work in all districts, a graph showing the growth of the ARA medical program from 1921-1922, and monthly medical and sanitary reports broken down by districts, 1921-1923. (Folder 3-4)
      Available on microfilm reel 602
  - Policy, Correspondence providing the general lay out of the Russian relief operation policies. Includes guidelines for districts managers and supervisors in administrative matters, minutes of conference of district supervisors at Moscow headquarters office, and other confidential correspondence relating to the policy making of the relief operation, 1921-1923. (Box 509, Folder 1)
    Available on microfilm reel 603
  - Polish and other European cooperation, Correspondence regarding some European nations wishing to contribute their relief efforts in Russia, 1921-1922. (Folder 2)
  - Ports, shipments, and storage, Correspondence reporting on the progress of requesting permission from local authorities to use ports and negotiating port usage in different cities for discharge of relief cargoes. Includes letters requesting information on facilities for discharging bulk grain at Constantinople and other available ports for handling ships with grain heading for the Volga regions, memoranda on inspection of Finish ports, pamphlets containing information on the Free Port of Hango, reports on port inspection, and one sketch of the harbor, 1921-1923. (Folder 3-5)
    Available on microfilm reels 603 and 604
  - Programs, Correspondence about establishing a feeding program for adults in the famine areas funded by the Congressional appropriation and a general plan to accomplish the adult corn program. Include monthly allocation schedules for adult corn ration within the districts, memoranda on the outline of liquidation procedure program expansion, letters of inquiries about the general resume of programs, food supply position for the feeding, transport of the whole Russian operation, and the latest development of the adult feeding program weekly menu, 1921-1923. (Box 510, Folder 1-2)
    Available on microfilm reel 605
  - Publicity file
    - General, Includes translations of newspaper clippings, copies of editorials, copies of excerpts of interviews, policy for publicity matters, a letter from Secretary of Commerce Herbert Hoover (Chairman of ARA) to President Harding on the general status of the effort to relieve the Russian famine, 1921-1923. (Folder 3-4)
      Available on microfilm reel 606
    - Press file (Box 511)
      - General, Newspaper clippings and typescript news summaries about the progress of the food remittance program and the pros and cons of Russian relief operations in general, 1921-1923. (Folder 1)
        Available on microfilm reel 607
      - Soviet press from Moscow, Includes copy of an extract from the Soviet Radio regarding the agreement between the Soviet Government and the ARA, 1921-1922. (Folder 2)
  - Purchases, Correspondence mainly about the purchasing of foodstuffs with Soviet gold and converting the gold in the U.S. to U.S. currency to purchase and ship food and seed supplies. Includes letters of credit, agreement covering the purchase of food supplies and seed in America by the ARA for the Russian Socialist Federative Soviet Republic, and summary of receipts and expenditures at Danzig on behalf of the Russian Socialist Federative Soviet Republic, 1921-1923.
    - 1921 August-1922 February (Folder 3-4)
    - 1922 March-1923 June (Folder 5-6)
      Available on microfilm reel 608
  - Relief (Box 512)
    - General relief
      - Letters and telegrams, Include some bulletins, pamphlets, and reports about political condition in Russia, 1919-1923. (Folder 1-2)
        Available on microfilm reels 608 and 609
      - History and policy. Correspondence regarding recommendations from all district supervisors of all phases of the Russian operation and decisions on the continuation of the operation in Russia. Include minutes of conference of district supervisors at Moscow, agreement with the American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee regarding operations in the Ukraine and White Russia, and circular letter to all district supervisors on the updates in policy
        - December, 1922 June- (Folder 3-4)
          Available on microfilm reel 609
        - 1923 (Folder 5)
    - International relief, Correspondence about the establishment of the International Russian Famine Relief Commission, which consists of representatives from various governments, various associations, and Red Cross societies to provide relief for the Russian famine. Includes guidelines to coordinate the work of these different national associations, assign work to each association within its resources, and provide a specific number of children or adults each association would guarantee in subsistence until the next harvest, the date they could undertake actual relief, and the financial resources of such associations available for this purpose, 1921 July-1922 September. (Box 513, Folder 1)
      Available on microfilm reel 610
    - International Russian Famine Relief Commission, Proceeding of the Riga conference that recognizes the extent of the disaster in Russia and agrees to establish a relief program through a joint effort of various organizations working on a strictly humanitarian basis and in agreement with the Russian government. Includes lists of names of delegates and representatives from each organization and minutes of meetings of conferences, 1921-1923.
      - General (Folder 2)
      - Correspondence regarding conferences in Paris and Brussels (Folder 3)
      - Proceedings and minutes of meetings (Folder 4-6)
    - Subcommittee meeting minutes and resolutions (Folder 7)
  - Repatriation, Correspondence requesting the assistance of ARA offices to locate missing family members and search for the whereabouts of relatives and families. Includes letters asking for permission to immediately get family members of Russian citizens out of Russia and concerning other immigration issues, 1921-1923. (Box 514)
    - General (Folder 1)
      Available on microfilm reel 611
    - 1921 August-1922 May (Folder 2-3)
    - 1922 May-October (Folder 4-5)
      Available on microfilm reel 612
    - 1922 October-1923 April (Box 515, Folder 1-2)
      Available on microfilm reels 612 and 613
  - Russian Northwestern government. Typescript of a report entitled "Relief Work with the Russian Northwestern Government by the American Relief Administration" by A. I. Ward (Folder 3)
    Available on microfilm reel 613
  - Student feeding and common wealth funds, Correspondence on the appeal for funds to help imprisoned ecclesiastics, intellectuals, and scientists expelled from Russia, and professors and students of the Superior Feminine Theological Institute of Kiev, 1921-1923. (Folder 4)
  - Supplies, Correspondence regarding the availability of food supplies. Include statements of estimated food requirements for children and adult soup kitchens and some statistical reports, 1921-1923.
    - 1921 June-1922 May (Folder 5-6)
    - 1922 May-1923 September (Box 516, Folder 1)
      Available on microfilm reel 614
  - Transportation
    - Internal shipments, November. Correspondence reports on transportation issues in shipping and transporting foodstuffs into Russia using local ports and railways in Warsaw and Riga. Includes summary covering arrivals discharge evacuation and figures given for each port and daily averages delivery of wheat and corns, 1922 March- (Folder 2)
    - Motors, Correspondence requesting purchases of replacement automobile parts and equipment. Includes list of prices for trucks, lists of vehicles purchased, inventory of automobiles and parts availability, and purchase orders for spare parts, 1921 August-1922 October. (Folder 3)
      Available on microfilm reel 615
  - Ukraine
    - General, Correspondence discussing the need for a relief program in the Ukraine. Includes one map of Ukraine showing famine areas and minutes of meeting between representatives of the ARA and the American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee about medical relief and total amount of medical supplies delivered to Ukraine and White Russia, 1921-1922. (Folder 4-5)
      Available on microfilm reels 615 and 616
    - Federation of Ukrainian Jews, Correspondence inquiring about the status of food distribution and delivery of food parcels. Includes some blank questionaire forms for beneficiaries, a pamphlet on the food remittances to Russia agreement, and some news clippings, 1922-1923. (Box 517, Folder 1-2)
      Available on microfilm reel 616
    - White Russia, Correspondence provides various data to support the needs for relief in the districts east of the armistice line. Includes an prized winning essay entitled "A Plan for the Organization of American Relief Administration Child Feeding System in Russia" by Johann Aichinger, a proposal stating specific objectives of the role of ARA in relief work in White Russia and the Ukraine east of the Curzon line reports from three German Socialists who have been in Russia about the political condition and upheaval in Russia, three reports from Maurice Pate on his trip to Minsk, a memorandum on openings for relief work by the American Friends Service in Russia, and some regulations of the Jewish United Committee for the relief of pogrom sufferers, 1920-1921. (Folder 3)
      Available on microfilm reel 617
    - From Paris office countries file
- Paris Office, Russia File, 1918-1926
  Available on microfilm reels 617-621
  Agreements, articles, correspondence, memoranda, minutes of meetings, notes, press reviews, printed matter, receipts, reports, statements, statistical records, and telegrams relating to relief operations in Russia and to the economic and political situation therein, arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - General (Box 518, Folder 1)
  - Agreements between the Russian Socialist Federative Soviet Republic and the ARA regarding relief operations (Folder 2)
  - Articles. Includes articles by Eleanor Franklin Egan and N. Orlow on the exchange of goods within Soviet Russia. Also includes some newspaper articles (Folder 3)
  - Correspondence
    - General (Folder 4-5)
    - 1918 November-December (Folder 6)
    - 1919
      - January-April (Folder 7)
      - May-December (Folder 8)
    - 1920-1926 (Folder 9)
      Available on microfilm reel 618
  - Memoranda
    - General (Folder 10)
    - Undated (Folder 11)
    - 1918 November-1919 July (Folder 12)
    - 1921-1923 (Folder 13)
  - Minutes of meetings (Folder 14)
  - Notes (Folder 15)
  - Press reviews (Folder 16)
  - Printed matter (Folder 17)
  - Receipts (Folder 18)
  - Reports
    - Undated (Folder 19)
    - 1919 (Box 519)
      - February-June (Folder 1)
      - Includes report on political and economic conditions in the liberated districts of Russia prepared by Van Arsdale Turner, ARA Baltic Mission, and a report on Soviet Russia transmitted by Ira N. Morris to Herbert Hoover, July-December. (Folder 2)
  - Statements. Includes statements from Herbert Hoover on food conditions and progress of Bolshevism in Russia (Folder 3)
  - Statistical records (Folder 4)
  - Subject file
    - Army communiqué containing intelligence information about the enemy (Folder 5-7)
      Available on microfilm reels 618 and 619
    - Children's relief operations
      - General
        - General (Folder 8)
          Available on microfilm reel 619
        - Correspondence (Folder 9)
        - Memoranda (Folder 10)
        - Reports (Folder 11)
        - Telegrams (Folder 12)
      - Delivery of food supplies (Folder 13)
    - Delivery of food supplies (Folder 14)
    - Kouban Mission
      - General (Folder 15)
      - Correspondence
        - General (Folder 16)
        - 1919 March-July (Folder 17)
      - Interview with V. I. Savitsky, special delegate of the government of General Denikin for industry, commerce, and food supply (extract) (Folder 18)
      - Lists of imports and materials (Folder 19)
      - Memoranda
        - General (Folder 20)
        - Undated (Folder 21)
        - 1919 January-July (Folder 22)
      - Notes (Folder 23)
      - Personnel records (Box 520, Folder 1)
      - Receipts (Folder 2)
      - Reports. Includes a report on the history of the Kouban Mission (Folder 3)
      - Statement (fragment) (Folder 4)
      - Statistical records (Folder 5)
      - Telegrams (Folder 6)
        Available on microfilm reel 620
      - Miscellany (Folder 7)
  - Telegrams
    - Undated (Folder 8)
    - 1918 November-December (Folder 9)
    - 1919
      - January-March (Folder 10)
      - April (Folder 11)
      - May (Folder 12)
      - June (Folder 13)
        Available on microfilm reel 621
      - July-August (Folder 14)
      - October-December (Folder 15)
      - 1920-1921 (Folder 16)
      - 1922 (Folder 17)
    - Miscellany (Folder 18)
- Russian Appreciation File, 1921-1923
  Available on microfilm reels 622-631
  Expressions of gratitude in the form of drawings, letters, and postcards received by the A.R.A. headquarters from Russian recipients of assistance.
  - General (Box 521)
    Available on microfilm reel 622
    - Drawings
    - Letters (Box 522)
      - General (Folder 1-5)
      - Government officials (Folder 6)
        Available on microfilm reel 623
      - Government officials (Box 523, Folder 1-2)
      - Intelligentsia (Folder 3-4)
      - Medical personnel (Folder 5-8)
        Available on microfilm reels 623 and 624
      - Medical personnel (Box 524, Folder 1-3)
        Available on microfilm reels 624 and 625
      - Students (Folder 4-6)
        Available on microfilm reels 624A and 625
  - Cities and regions (Box 525)
    - General (Folder 1)
      Available on microfilm reel 625
    - Astrakhan (Folder 2)
    - Bashkiria (Folder 3)
    - Cheliabinsk (Folder 4-5)
    - Crimea
      - General (Folder 6-7)
        Available on microfilm reels 625 and 626
      - Letters from German colony (Folder 8)
        Available on microfilm reel 626
      - Postcards depicting local views (Folder 9)
    - Daghestan (Box 526, Folder 1)
    - Georgia (Folder 2)
    - Kazan (Folder 3)
    - Kharkov (Folder 4)
    - Kirghizia (Folder 5)
    - Minsk (Folder 6)
      Available on microfilm reel 627
    - Moscow (Folder 7-8)
    - Odessa (Box 527, Folder 1-2)
    - Orenburg (Folder 3-4)
    - Petrograd (Folder 5)
    - Rostov (Folder 6)
    - Samara (Folder 7)
    - Saratov (Folder 8)
      Available on microfilm reel 628
    - Saratov (Box 528, Folder 1-2)
    - Simbirsk (Folder 3-7)
      Available on microfilm reels 628 and 629
    - Simbirsk (Box 529, Folder 1)
      Available on microfilm reel 629
    - Ufa (Folder 2-6)
      Available on microfilm reels 629 and 630
    - Ukraine (Box 530, Folder 1-4)
      Available on microfilm reels 630 and 631
    - Vitebsk (Folder 5)
      Available on microfilm reel 631
- General Office, Russia File, 1921-1923
  Available on microfilm reels 631-641